<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2025-10-05T18:44:46+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">UbbyReads</title><subtitle>read, write, sleep</subtitle><entry><title type="html">To the Lighthouse - Virginia Woolf</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/classics/modernist%20literature/literary%20fiction/feminist%20literature/psychological%20fiction/2025/07/24/To-The-Lighthouse/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To the Lighthouse - Virginia Woolf" /><published>2025-07-24T12:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-24T12:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/classics/modernist%20literature/literary%20fiction/feminist%20literature/psychological%20fiction/2025/07/24/To-The-Lighthouse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/classics/modernist%20literature/literary%20fiction/feminist%20literature/psychological%20fiction/2025/07/24/To-The-Lighthouse/"><![CDATA[<p>Virginia Woolf (1882–1941) was a central figure in the modernist literary movement and a pioneer of stream-of-consciousness narrative. Her work delves deeply into time, memory, perception, and the interior lives of her characters. Through novels like <em>Mrs Dalloway</em>, <em>Orlando</em>, and <em>To the Lighthouse</em>, Woolf reshaped what fiction could do—turning inward, exploring consciousness and the passing of time with radical clarity and emotional nuance.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/image/woolf.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/woolf.jpg" alt="Virginia Woolfe" /></a></p>

<p>A friend recommended this to me, and I picked it up mostly out of curiosity. I’d never properly ventured into stream-of-consciousness or modernist fiction, and Virginia Woolf seemed like the kind of author whose work I should at least try once. <em>To the Lighthouse</em> felt like the natural starting point. I’d heard all about how it breaks convention, how it shifts perspectives, how it avoids traditional plot. I knew going in that it wouldn’t be a page-turner. Still, I wasn’t quite prepared for what it actually was: dense, meandering, incredibly interior, and quietly demanding.</p>

<p>Let’s get the obvious out of the way first: this is probably the densest book I’ve read so far. Not because it’s filled with academic jargon or complicated plot threads, but because every sentence carries weight. Nothing is tossed off casually, even though it <em>sounds</em> casual. Thoughts overlap, time shifts mid-paragraph, and characters’ minds unfold in a sort of slow-motion drift. The humor, when it appears, is so dry you might miss it entirely if you blink. The Britishness of it all is almost exaggerated. One line that stuck out: “The very stone one kicks with one’s boot will outlast Shakespeare.” That’s the kind of sentence that both humbles you and makes you want to close the book for a moment.</p>

<p>What surprised me most, though, was how the book made me feel — or rather, how it didn’t. I didn’t come away from <em>To the Lighthouse</em> feeling anything in particular. Not joy, not sadness, not even confusion. Just… blank. And that blankness sat with me longer than I expected. I kept thinking: did I miss something? Was I not paying enough attention? Or was the point <em>that</em> subtle?</p>

<p>I get that Woolf wasn’t trying to tell a story in the traditional sense. There’s no real plot to speak of, and she never pretended there would be. That’s kind of the whole point. The focus is inward — on perception, memory, interiority. It’s about how people <em>think</em>, how they misunderstand each other, how time passes without permission or acknowledgment. And on that front, it succeeds. If you read Woolf’s essay “Modern Fiction,” it’s clear that this book is a working-out of her ideas in fiction form. She wanted to capture life as it is lived: not as a chain of events, but as a stream of impressions and unspoken thoughts. It’s ambitious. It’s brave. And it clearly changed how people thought about what a novel could be.</p>

<p>But at the same time, I kept circling around the same question: what do I take away from this? I mean, beyond admiration for the craft, what am I <em>feeling</em>? What has shifted in me?</p>

<p>Don’t get me wrong — there’s a lot to admire. The subtlety is incredible. Woolf can say everything with almost nothing. A comment about the weather becomes a gesture of love. An awkward silence becomes a portrait of a failing marriage. Her narrator fades into the background, just hovering behind the characters’ eyes, giving us access to their deepest uncertainties without ever overexplaining. Some moments — like Lily painting, or the sudden intrusion of time and loss in the “Time Passes” section — were among the most vivid I’ve encountered in any novel.</p>

<p>And Woolf’s treatment of time is fascinating. The way she speeds it up, slows it down, folds it in on itself. Whole years pass in half a page. Death arrives mid-sentence. Children grow up, houses change, and it all just… happens. No drama, no build-up. Just life, slipping by quietly.</p>

<p>Characters like Mr. Ramsay are surprisingly complex — irritating, but fully formed. There are layers to them. You’re never told what to think, you just sit with their contradictions and draw your own conclusions. And maybe that’s the book’s real strength: it invites you to sit in ambiguity. To not understand everything. To resist the urge to wrap it all up in meaning.</p>

<p>And yet, after all that, I’m still left with that floating, unresolved feeling. Maybe that’s exactly what Woolf wanted. Maybe the point <em>was</em> the detachment. The emptiness. The fact that people live side by side, thinking and feeling in radically different ways, and never quite reaching each other.</p>

<p>I’m glad I read it. It pushed me. It made me slow down. It reminded me that novels don’t have to tell stories the way we’re used to. But I can’t say I loved it. I respected it. I admired the control and the ambition. But it didn’t move me. At least not in a way I can name.</p>

<p>Will I read Woolf again? Probably. I’m curious now — curious enough to try <em>Night and Day</em> or <em>Jacob’s Room</em> and see if they strike a different chord. But for now, <em>To the Lighthouse</em> sits in that strange category of books I’m glad to have read, but don’t quite know what to do with after.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Classics" /><category term="Modernist Literature" /><category term="Literary Fiction" /><category term="Feminist Literature" /><category term="Psychological Fiction" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Virginia Woolf (1882–1941) was a central figure in the modernist literary movement and a pioneer of stream-of-consciousness narrative. Her work delves deeply into time, memory, perception, and the interior lives of her characters. Through novels like Mrs Dalloway, Orlando, and To the Lighthouse, Woolf reshaped what fiction could do—turning inward, exploring consciousness and the passing of time with radical clarity and emotional nuance. A friend recommended this to me, and I picked it up mostly out of curiosity. I’d never properly ventured into stream-of-consciousness or modernist fiction, and Virginia Woolf seemed like the kind of author whose work I should at least try once. To the Lighthouse felt like the natural starting point. I’d heard all about how it breaks convention, how it shifts perspectives, how it avoids traditional plot. I knew going in that it wouldn’t be a page-turner. Still, I wasn’t quite prepared for what it actually was: dense, meandering, incredibly interior, and quietly demanding. Let’s get the obvious out of the way first: this is probably the densest book I’ve read so far. Not because it’s filled with academic jargon or complicated plot threads, but because every sentence carries weight. Nothing is tossed off casually, even though it sounds casual. Thoughts overlap, time shifts mid-paragraph, and characters’ minds unfold in a sort of slow-motion drift. The humor, when it appears, is so dry you might miss it entirely if you blink. The Britishness of it all is almost exaggerated. One line that stuck out: “The very stone one kicks with one’s boot will outlast Shakespeare.” That’s the kind of sentence that both humbles you and makes you want to close the book for a moment. What surprised me most, though, was how the book made me feel — or rather, how it didn’t. I didn’t come away from To the Lighthouse feeling anything in particular. Not joy, not sadness, not even confusion. Just… blank. And that blankness sat with me longer than I expected. I kept thinking: did I miss something? Was I not paying enough attention? Or was the point that subtle? I get that Woolf wasn’t trying to tell a story in the traditional sense. There’s no real plot to speak of, and she never pretended there would be. That’s kind of the whole point. The focus is inward — on perception, memory, interiority. It’s about how people think, how they misunderstand each other, how time passes without permission or acknowledgment. And on that front, it succeeds. If you read Woolf’s essay “Modern Fiction,” it’s clear that this book is a working-out of her ideas in fiction form. She wanted to capture life as it is lived: not as a chain of events, but as a stream of impressions and unspoken thoughts. It’s ambitious. It’s brave. And it clearly changed how people thought about what a novel could be. But at the same time, I kept circling around the same question: what do I take away from this? I mean, beyond admiration for the craft, what am I feeling? What has shifted in me? Don’t get me wrong — there’s a lot to admire. The subtlety is incredible. Woolf can say everything with almost nothing. A comment about the weather becomes a gesture of love. An awkward silence becomes a portrait of a failing marriage. Her narrator fades into the background, just hovering behind the characters’ eyes, giving us access to their deepest uncertainties without ever overexplaining. Some moments — like Lily painting, or the sudden intrusion of time and loss in the “Time Passes” section — were among the most vivid I’ve encountered in any novel. And Woolf’s treatment of time is fascinating. The way she speeds it up, slows it down, folds it in on itself. Whole years pass in half a page. Death arrives mid-sentence. Children grow up, houses change, and it all just… happens. No drama, no build-up. Just life, slipping by quietly. Characters like Mr. Ramsay are surprisingly complex — irritating, but fully formed. There are layers to them. You’re never told what to think, you just sit with their contradictions and draw your own conclusions. And maybe that’s the book’s real strength: it invites you to sit in ambiguity. To not understand everything. To resist the urge to wrap it all up in meaning. And yet, after all that, I’m still left with that floating, unresolved feeling. Maybe that’s exactly what Woolf wanted. Maybe the point was the detachment. The emptiness. The fact that people live side by side, thinking and feeling in radically different ways, and never quite reaching each other. I’m glad I read it. It pushed me. It made me slow down. It reminded me that novels don’t have to tell stories the way we’re used to. But I can’t say I loved it. I respected it. I admired the control and the ambition. But it didn’t move me. At least not in a way I can name. Will I read Woolf again? Probably. I’m curious now — curious enough to try Night and Day or Jacob’s Room and see if they strike a different chord. But for now, To the Lighthouse sits in that strange category of books I’m glad to have read, but don’t quite know what to do with after.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Izu Dancer - Yasunari Kawabata</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/classics/japanese%20literature/literary%20fiction/modernism/japanese%20modernism/2025/07/18/The-Izu-Dancer/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Izu Dancer - Yasunari Kawabata" /><published>2025-07-18T12:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-18T12:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/classics/japanese%20literature/literary%20fiction/modernism/japanese%20modernism/2025/07/18/The-Izu-Dancer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/classics/japanese%20literature/literary%20fiction/modernism/japanese%20modernism/2025/07/18/The-Izu-Dancer/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Yasunari Kawabata</strong> (1899–1972) is one of Japan’s most celebrated authors and was awarded the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1968. Known for his poetic and understated prose, Kawabata’s work often explores themes of beauty, loneliness, and the fleeting nature of human connection. Drawing deeply from traditional Japanese aesthetics and modernist sensibilities, his stories invite readers into a quiet, contemplative world where emotions are conveyed through subtle gestures and evocative imagery. <em>The Izu Dancer</em> (1926) is one of his early works, capturing the delicate emotional landscape of youth and longing with characteristic grace.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/image/kawabata.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/kawabata.jpg" alt="Yasunari Kawabata" /></a></p>

<p>Finishing <em>The Izu Dancer</em> left me with a bittersweet feeling—a quiet kind of sadness that lingers long after the last page. It’s the kind of melancholy that’s not overwhelming or dramatic but subtle, the kind you carry around like a soft shadow. At times, though, I found myself wondering whether I had actually read a story or just experienced a series of poetic moments loosely stitched together. The narrative doesn’t follow a clear plot arc or a conventional story structure. Instead, it flows more like impressions, fleeting glances, and small, almost dreamlike interactions.</p>

<p>This subtlety is part of what makes Kawabata’s writing so unique. There’s a gentleness to the emotions that feels almost like a whisper—tender but not fully formed into romance or drama. It’s more about the feeling of yearning and distance, the unspoken tension between people, and the transient nature of connection. Still, while I admired this delicate approach, there were moments where I found myself craving more clarity or movement in the story. It felt a bit frustrating to hover on the edges without ever fully stepping into the characters’ worlds or their emotions.</p>

<p>One scene I kept thinking about was the dancer’s performance by the fire. It’s meant to be a central, emotionally charged moment, but for me, it didn’t hit as powerfully as I expected. Maybe I was looking for something more vivid or intense, but instead, Kawabata presents it in this quiet, understated way. The dance feels more symbolic, an ethereal expression of fleeting beauty and impermanence. I’m not sure I fully understood why this moment held such weight in the story, but I suspect that’s intentional—Kawabata invites readers to feel rather than analyze, to experience the fragility of that moment instead of dissecting it.</p>

<p>The student’s melancholy feels layered and complex. On one level, there’s a tender attraction to the dancer, a subtle affection that never quite develops into anything tangible. But deeper than that, the sadness seems rooted in the inevitability of leaving—to return to a world that is more rigid, more defined, and less open to those fragile connections. There’s this sense that fleeting moments of beauty and human warmth are precious precisely because they cannot last. The story captures that feeling of knowing something wonderful is slipping away before it’s even fully grasped.</p>

<p>Reading <em>The Izu Dancer</em> also made me reflect on Kawabata’s style and cultural context. Coming from Japan’s early 20th century, his work often explores themes of impermanence, beauty, and loneliness through sparse but evocative prose. His storytelling asks readers to slow down, to pay attention to what’s hinted at in silences and what lingers between the lines. It’s a very different experience from plot-driven Western fiction, and it demands a kind of patient engagement that isn’t always easy but can be deeply rewarding.</p>

<p>After this, I’m curious to dive into more of Kawabata’s work. <em>Snow Country</em> is the obvious next step—it promises a similar mood but darker, with even more nuanced explorations of love and isolation. Yet, I’m also cautious. This kind of subtle, impressionistic storytelling isn’t for everyone, and it might not always resonate with me. There’s a hypnotic beauty in it, but also a distance that can feel frustrating if you’re craving a more direct emotional connection.</p>

<p>Still, <em>The Izu Dancer</em> is a worthwhile read. It’s like a quiet song that stays with you, soft but persistent, reminding you of the transient moments in life that matter most because they don’t last. It makes you appreciate those brief encounters and feelings that flicker and fade but somehow leave a mark on the heart.</p>

<p>Would I recommend it? Definitely, if you’re open to stories that don’t wrap everything up neatly and prefer moods and impressions over clear-cut narratives. It’s a gentle introduction to Kawabata’s world and leaves you thinking long after you finish.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The dancer’s smile was like a secret, fragile and fleeting, as if it could vanish with the morning mist.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The student felt a quiet sorrow, not loud or urgent, but like the soft ache of a fading dream.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“In that moment, the dancer’s movement seemed to suspend time itself—an ephemeral beauty that could never be held.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“He realized how the inevitability of parting gave weight to every shared glance and every silent goodbye.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“There was a loneliness in the hills, a silence that spoke louder than words, and it filled his heart with something he could not name.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Classics" /><category term="Japanese Literature" /><category term="Literary Fiction" /><category term="Modernism" /><category term="Japanese Modernism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Yasunari Kawabata (1899–1972) is one of Japan’s most celebrated authors and was awarded the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1968. Known for his poetic and understated prose, Kawabata’s work often explores themes of beauty, loneliness, and the fleeting nature of human connection. Drawing deeply from traditional Japanese aesthetics and modernist sensibilities, his stories invite readers into a quiet, contemplative world where emotions are conveyed through subtle gestures and evocative imagery. The Izu Dancer (1926) is one of his early works, capturing the delicate emotional landscape of youth and longing with characteristic grace. Finishing The Izu Dancer left me with a bittersweet feeling—a quiet kind of sadness that lingers long after the last page. It’s the kind of melancholy that’s not overwhelming or dramatic but subtle, the kind you carry around like a soft shadow. At times, though, I found myself wondering whether I had actually read a story or just experienced a series of poetic moments loosely stitched together. The narrative doesn’t follow a clear plot arc or a conventional story structure. Instead, it flows more like impressions, fleeting glances, and small, almost dreamlike interactions. This subtlety is part of what makes Kawabata’s writing so unique. There’s a gentleness to the emotions that feels almost like a whisper—tender but not fully formed into romance or drama. It’s more about the feeling of yearning and distance, the unspoken tension between people, and the transient nature of connection. Still, while I admired this delicate approach, there were moments where I found myself craving more clarity or movement in the story. It felt a bit frustrating to hover on the edges without ever fully stepping into the characters’ worlds or their emotions. One scene I kept thinking about was the dancer’s performance by the fire. It’s meant to be a central, emotionally charged moment, but for me, it didn’t hit as powerfully as I expected. Maybe I was looking for something more vivid or intense, but instead, Kawabata presents it in this quiet, understated way. The dance feels more symbolic, an ethereal expression of fleeting beauty and impermanence. I’m not sure I fully understood why this moment held such weight in the story, but I suspect that’s intentional—Kawabata invites readers to feel rather than analyze, to experience the fragility of that moment instead of dissecting it. The student’s melancholy feels layered and complex. On one level, there’s a tender attraction to the dancer, a subtle affection that never quite develops into anything tangible. But deeper than that, the sadness seems rooted in the inevitability of leaving—to return to a world that is more rigid, more defined, and less open to those fragile connections. There’s this sense that fleeting moments of beauty and human warmth are precious precisely because they cannot last. The story captures that feeling of knowing something wonderful is slipping away before it’s even fully grasped. Reading The Izu Dancer also made me reflect on Kawabata’s style and cultural context. Coming from Japan’s early 20th century, his work often explores themes of impermanence, beauty, and loneliness through sparse but evocative prose. His storytelling asks readers to slow down, to pay attention to what’s hinted at in silences and what lingers between the lines. It’s a very different experience from plot-driven Western fiction, and it demands a kind of patient engagement that isn’t always easy but can be deeply rewarding. After this, I’m curious to dive into more of Kawabata’s work. Snow Country is the obvious next step—it promises a similar mood but darker, with even more nuanced explorations of love and isolation. Yet, I’m also cautious. This kind of subtle, impressionistic storytelling isn’t for everyone, and it might not always resonate with me. There’s a hypnotic beauty in it, but also a distance that can feel frustrating if you’re craving a more direct emotional connection. Still, The Izu Dancer is a worthwhile read. It’s like a quiet song that stays with you, soft but persistent, reminding you of the transient moments in life that matter most because they don’t last. It makes you appreciate those brief encounters and feelings that flicker and fade but somehow leave a mark on the heart. Would I recommend it? Definitely, if you’re open to stories that don’t wrap everything up neatly and prefer moods and impressions over clear-cut narratives. It’s a gentle introduction to Kawabata’s world and leaves you thinking long after you finish. “The dancer’s smile was like a secret, fragile and fleeting, as if it could vanish with the morning mist.” “The student felt a quiet sorrow, not loud or urgent, but like the soft ache of a fading dream.” “In that moment, the dancer’s movement seemed to suspend time itself—an ephemeral beauty that could never be held.” “He realized how the inevitability of parting gave weight to every shared glance and every silent goodbye.” “There was a loneliness in the hills, a silence that spoke louder than words, and it filled his heart with something he could not name.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Songs of Innocence and of Experience - William Blake</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/poetry/romanticism/illuminated%20verse/poetry%20that%20listens%20back/metaphysical%20poetry/2025/07/17/Songs-of-Innocence-and-of-Experience/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Songs of Innocence and of Experience - William Blake" /><published>2025-07-17T12:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-17T12:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/poetry/romanticism/illuminated%20verse/poetry%20that%20listens%20back/metaphysical%20poetry/2025/07/17/Songs-of-Innocence-and-of-Experience</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/poetry/romanticism/illuminated%20verse/poetry%20that%20listens%20back/metaphysical%20poetry/2025/07/17/Songs-of-Innocence-and-of-Experience/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>William Blake (1757–1827)</strong> was a poet, painter, and printmaker whose work was largely unrecognized in his lifetime but has since become central to English literature and art. A visionary from an early age, Blake claimed to see angels in trees and speak with spirits — experiences that shaped a body of work marked by spiritual intensity, radical politics, and formal innovation.</p>

<p>He trained as an engraver, and much of his poetry was self-published in “illuminated” books — works in which text and image were etched, printed, and colored by hand. His best-known collections, <em>Songs of Innocence</em> (1789) and <em>Songs of Experience</em> (1794), explore the tensions between purity and corruption, nature and society, childlike faith and institutional power.</p>

<p>Though often considered part of the Romantic movement, Blake defies easy categorization. His writing is at once mystical and grounded, deeply personal and fiercely political. He distrusted authority, both religious and governmental, and imagined a world where the human spirit might be free to create, love, and rebel.</p>

<p>Today, Blake is seen as one of the most original and influential figures in English literature — a poet who spoke not to his age but to the ages to come.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/image/blake.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/blake.jpg" alt="William Blake" /></a></p>

<p>I went into this with zero expectations. I’d heard of Blake, obviously — the Romantic mystic guy with strange symbols and angels and maybe some madness — but <em>Songs of Experience</em> was my first real encounter with him. What caught me off guard was how quiet and sharp the whole thing is. There’s no grand shouting, no theatrical lament — just this slow, calm disillusionment that sneaks up on you and stays.</p>

<p>The contrast between <em>Innocence</em> and <em>Experience</em> is where the power lives. You start with the gentle glow of childhood, faith, trust, softness — and then <em>Experience</em> enters like a sudden fog. Not cold, not loud — just there. It’s like Blake’s telling you: “See? You thought you understood the world.” And then he turns it, just a little, and now nothing is simple anymore.</p>

<p>Some parts felt too distant, too abstract, and I’ll admit a few poems didn’t land for me. But then you get to ones like <em>A Dream</em>, <em>Holy Thursday</em>, <em>The Little Girl Lost</em>, <em>The Little Girl Found</em>, <em>The Little Vagabond</em>, and <em>The Schoolboy</em> — and they just <em>work</em>. They’re sad without being sentimental, critical without being bitter. Especially <em>The Little Vagabond</em> — that voice, that raw honesty. It sticks.</p>

<p>The tone in <em>Songs of Experience</em> isn’t angry, but there’s tension underneath. You feel how much Blake sees — corruption, hypocrisy, systems pretending to be salvation. It’s not a total rejection of belief, but a confrontation with the way the world poisons it. Especially in poems like <em>Holy Thursday</em>, where the “innocence” of children is framed against institutional cruelty. Blake doesn’t say “these are bad people” — he says, “Look. Just <em>look</em>.” And somehow that’s worse.</p>

<p>I didn’t see the illustrations, just read the poems plain. But even without the visuals, there’s an illuminated quality to it — not in the sense of enlightenment, but in how Blake seems to be writing <em>from</em> somewhere else. Not above us, not outside — just adjacent. Like he’s caught between earth and dream, reporting back.</p>

<p>And now I’m curious. I want to try <em>The Marriage of Heaven and Hell</em>, maybe even one of his prophetic works — though I hear they’re dense. But I get the feeling that if <em>Songs of Experience</em> found a way into me, then somewhere down the line, those wilder works might too.</p>

<p>Blake’s not easy. Not always clear. But there’s something oddly honest in that. Experience isn’t tidy. Neither is he.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>HOLY THURSDAY</strong></p>

  <p>Is this a holy thing to see
   In a rich and fruitful land,—
Babes reduced to misery,
   Fed with cold and usurous hand?
Is that trembling cry a song?
   Can it be a song of joy?
And so many children poor?
   It is a land of poverty!
And their sun does never shine,
   And their fields are bleak and bare,
And their ways are filled with thorns,
   It is eternal winter there.
For where’er the sun does shine,
   And where’er the rain does fall,
Babe can never hunger there,
   Nor poverty the mind appal.”
   
  &gt;<strong>THE SCHOOLBOY</strong>
  &gt;
I love to rise in a summer morn,
   When the birds sing on every tree;
The distant huntsman winds his horn,
   And the skylark sings with me:
   O what sweet company!
But to go to school in a summer morn,—
   O it drives all joy away!
Under a cruel eye outworn,
   The little ones spend the day
   In sighing and dismay.
Ah then at times I drooping sit,
   And spend many an anxious hour;
Nor in my book can I take delight,
   Nor sit in learning’s bower,
   Worn through with the dreary shower.”
“How can the bird that is born for joy
   Sit in a cage and sing?
How can a child, when fears annoy,
   But droop his tender wing,
   And forget his youthful spring!
O father and mother if buds are nipped,
   And blossoms blown away;
And if the tender plants are stripped
   Of their joy in the springing day,
   By sorrow and care’s dismay,—
How shall the summer arise in joy,
   Or the summer fruits appear?
Or how shall we gather what griefs destroy,
   Or bless the mellowing year,
   When the blasts of winter appear?”</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Poetry" /><category term="Romanticism" /><category term="Illuminated verse" /><category term="Poetry that listens back" /><category term="Metaphysical Poetry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[William Blake (1757–1827) was a poet, painter, and printmaker whose work was largely unrecognized in his lifetime but has since become central to English literature and art. A visionary from an early age, Blake claimed to see angels in trees and speak with spirits — experiences that shaped a body of work marked by spiritual intensity, radical politics, and formal innovation. He trained as an engraver, and much of his poetry was self-published in “illuminated” books — works in which text and image were etched, printed, and colored by hand. His best-known collections, Songs of Innocence (1789) and Songs of Experience (1794), explore the tensions between purity and corruption, nature and society, childlike faith and institutional power. Though often considered part of the Romantic movement, Blake defies easy categorization. His writing is at once mystical and grounded, deeply personal and fiercely political. He distrusted authority, both religious and governmental, and imagined a world where the human spirit might be free to create, love, and rebel. Today, Blake is seen as one of the most original and influential figures in English literature — a poet who spoke not to his age but to the ages to come. I went into this with zero expectations. I’d heard of Blake, obviously — the Romantic mystic guy with strange symbols and angels and maybe some madness — but Songs of Experience was my first real encounter with him. What caught me off guard was how quiet and sharp the whole thing is. There’s no grand shouting, no theatrical lament — just this slow, calm disillusionment that sneaks up on you and stays. The contrast between Innocence and Experience is where the power lives. You start with the gentle glow of childhood, faith, trust, softness — and then Experience enters like a sudden fog. Not cold, not loud — just there. It’s like Blake’s telling you: “See? You thought you understood the world.” And then he turns it, just a little, and now nothing is simple anymore. Some parts felt too distant, too abstract, and I’ll admit a few poems didn’t land for me. But then you get to ones like A Dream, Holy Thursday, The Little Girl Lost, The Little Girl Found, The Little Vagabond, and The Schoolboy — and they just work. They’re sad without being sentimental, critical without being bitter. Especially The Little Vagabond — that voice, that raw honesty. It sticks. The tone in Songs of Experience isn’t angry, but there’s tension underneath. You feel how much Blake sees — corruption, hypocrisy, systems pretending to be salvation. It’s not a total rejection of belief, but a confrontation with the way the world poisons it. Especially in poems like Holy Thursday, where the “innocence” of children is framed against institutional cruelty. Blake doesn’t say “these are bad people” — he says, “Look. Just look.” And somehow that’s worse. I didn’t see the illustrations, just read the poems plain. But even without the visuals, there’s an illuminated quality to it — not in the sense of enlightenment, but in how Blake seems to be writing from somewhere else. Not above us, not outside — just adjacent. Like he’s caught between earth and dream, reporting back. And now I’m curious. I want to try The Marriage of Heaven and Hell, maybe even one of his prophetic works — though I hear they’re dense. But I get the feeling that if Songs of Experience found a way into me, then somewhere down the line, those wilder works might too. Blake’s not easy. Not always clear. But there’s something oddly honest in that. Experience isn’t tidy. Neither is he. HOLY THURSDAY Is this a holy thing to see    In a rich and fruitful land,— Babes reduced to misery,    Fed with cold and usurous hand? Is that trembling cry a song?    Can it be a song of joy? And so many children poor?    It is a land of poverty! And their sun does never shine,    And their fields are bleak and bare, And their ways are filled with thorns,    It is eternal winter there. For where’er the sun does shine,    And where’er the rain does fall, Babe can never hunger there,    Nor poverty the mind appal.”      &gt;THE SCHOOLBOY   &gt; I love to rise in a summer morn,    When the birds sing on every tree; The distant huntsman winds his horn,    And the skylark sings with me:    O what sweet company! But to go to school in a summer morn,—    O it drives all joy away! Under a cruel eye outworn,    The little ones spend the day    In sighing and dismay. Ah then at times I drooping sit,    And spend many an anxious hour; Nor in my book can I take delight,    Nor sit in learning’s bower,    Worn through with the dreary shower.” “How can the bird that is born for joy    Sit in a cage and sing? How can a child, when fears annoy,    But droop his tender wing,    And forget his youthful spring! O father and mother if buds are nipped,    And blossoms blown away; And if the tender plants are stripped    Of their joy in the springing day,    By sorrow and care’s dismay,— How shall the summer arise in joy,    Or the summer fruits appear? Or how shall we gather what griefs destroy,    Or bless the mellowing year,    When the blasts of winter appear?”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Death of an Official - Anton Chekhov</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/absurdist%20satire/bureaucratic%20comedy/absurdist/psychological%20realism/2025/07/17/The-Death-of-an-Official/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Death of an Official - Anton Chekhov" /><published>2025-07-17T12:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-17T12:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/absurdist%20satire/bureaucratic%20comedy/absurdist/psychological%20realism/2025/07/17/The-Death-of-an-Official</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/absurdist%20satire/bureaucratic%20comedy/absurdist/psychological%20realism/2025/07/17/The-Death-of-an-Official/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Anton Chekhov</strong> (1860–1904) was a Russian playwright and short story master, known for his subtle, layered portraits of ordinary people caught in the quiet absurdities of life. A doctor by profession, Chekhov brought a clinical eye to his characters — not to judge them, but to reveal the fragile contradictions they carry. His stories often feel simple at first glance, but they unravel into moments of quiet tragedy, awkward comedy, and aching humanity.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/image/anton.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/anton.jpeg" alt="Anton Chekhov" /></a></p>

<p>It’s funny — just a sneeze. That’s how it starts.</p>

<p>Ivan Dmitritch Chervyakov, a minor civil servant with a name that sounds almost like “worm,” sneezes during a night at the theater. Unfortunately, the sneeze lands on the bald head of General Brizzhalov, a high-ranking official. Chervyakov panics. Apologizes. The general waves it off. End of story?</p>

<p>Not even close.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Pardon, your Excellency, I… I didn’t mean to…”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is a story about how anxiety eats people alive. Chervyakov becomes convinced that his sneeze has ruined everything — his reputation, his job, his life. So he apologizes again. And again. Each time he tries to explain himself, it becomes more excruciating. We, the readers, can see it unraveling in slow motion. And it’s hilarious. And horrifying.</p>

<p>This is social anxiety before the term existed — distilled into one man’s slow-motion emotional collapse. And what’s wild is that the general never actually threatens him. He doesn’t yell. He barely reacts. It’s not the system that crushes Chervyakov — it’s his <em>perception</em> of the system. The fear of authority becomes so intense it turns into a death sentence.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“He reached home, lay down on the sofa, and died.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Just like that.</p>

<p>Chekhov doesn’t over-explain it. There’s no dramatic twist. No tragic past revealed. He just <em>dies</em>. From shame? From exhaustion? From being ignored after putting himself through so much emotional chaos?</p>

<p>It’s absurd. And it’s perfect.</p>

<p>What struck me most was how <em>small</em> the problem was. And how <em>huge</em> it became.</p>

<p>Chervyakov doesn’t die from illness or violence. He dies from overthinking. From shame. From needing approval in a world that doesn’t really care.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“He wanted to protest, but his voice failed him.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s heartbreaking, and also a little bit hilarious, because who hasn’t spiraled after saying the wrong thing in public? Who hasn’t replayed an interaction a hundred times, imagining how you looked, how you sounded? Chekhov gets it — and he turns it into art.</p>

<p>Chekhov doesn’t moralize. He just points a quiet finger at how we live — how absurd it is to be so fragile, so status-obsessed, so consumed with appearances that a sneeze can undo a man.</p>

<p><em>The Death of an Official</em> is short, sharp, and strangely timeless. It made me laugh, then wince, then sit very still. I don’t feel like I need to reread it anytime soon. Not because I didn’t like it — but because it already said what it needed to. Clearly. Completely.</p>

<p>Like all great short stories, it leaves behind a faint ache — and the slight worry that maybe, just maybe, you too could die from a sneeze.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“He did not sleep all night, and was tormented by vague reminiscences.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I am not apologizing in order to receive a reward…”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You are making fun of me, sir,” the general said, turning away with a look of disgust.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“He got home, lay down on the sofa, and died.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Absurdist satire" /><category term="Bureaucratic comedy" /><category term="Absurdist" /><category term="Psychological realism" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Anton Chekhov (1860–1904) was a Russian playwright and short story master, known for his subtle, layered portraits of ordinary people caught in the quiet absurdities of life. A doctor by profession, Chekhov brought a clinical eye to his characters — not to judge them, but to reveal the fragile contradictions they carry. His stories often feel simple at first glance, but they unravel into moments of quiet tragedy, awkward comedy, and aching humanity. It’s funny — just a sneeze. That’s how it starts. Ivan Dmitritch Chervyakov, a minor civil servant with a name that sounds almost like “worm,” sneezes during a night at the theater. Unfortunately, the sneeze lands on the bald head of General Brizzhalov, a high-ranking official. Chervyakov panics. Apologizes. The general waves it off. End of story? Not even close. “Pardon, your Excellency, I… I didn’t mean to…” This is a story about how anxiety eats people alive. Chervyakov becomes convinced that his sneeze has ruined everything — his reputation, his job, his life. So he apologizes again. And again. Each time he tries to explain himself, it becomes more excruciating. We, the readers, can see it unraveling in slow motion. And it’s hilarious. And horrifying. This is social anxiety before the term existed — distilled into one man’s slow-motion emotional collapse. And what’s wild is that the general never actually threatens him. He doesn’t yell. He barely reacts. It’s not the system that crushes Chervyakov — it’s his perception of the system. The fear of authority becomes so intense it turns into a death sentence. “He reached home, lay down on the sofa, and died.” Just like that. Chekhov doesn’t over-explain it. There’s no dramatic twist. No tragic past revealed. He just dies. From shame? From exhaustion? From being ignored after putting himself through so much emotional chaos? It’s absurd. And it’s perfect. What struck me most was how small the problem was. And how huge it became. Chervyakov doesn’t die from illness or violence. He dies from overthinking. From shame. From needing approval in a world that doesn’t really care. “He wanted to protest, but his voice failed him.” It’s heartbreaking, and also a little bit hilarious, because who hasn’t spiraled after saying the wrong thing in public? Who hasn’t replayed an interaction a hundred times, imagining how you looked, how you sounded? Chekhov gets it — and he turns it into art. Chekhov doesn’t moralize. He just points a quiet finger at how we live — how absurd it is to be so fragile, so status-obsessed, so consumed with appearances that a sneeze can undo a man. The Death of an Official is short, sharp, and strangely timeless. It made me laugh, then wince, then sit very still. I don’t feel like I need to reread it anytime soon. Not because I didn’t like it — but because it already said what it needed to. Clearly. Completely. Like all great short stories, it leaves behind a faint ache — and the slight worry that maybe, just maybe, you too could die from a sneeze. “He did not sleep all night, and was tormented by vague reminiscences.” “I am not apologizing in order to receive a reward…” “You are making fun of me, sir,” the general said, turning away with a look of disgust. “He got home, lay down on the sofa, and died.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Selected Poems - Constantine P. Cavafy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/modernist%20poetry/lyric%20poetry/elegy/philosophical%20poetry/historical%20poetry/symbolist%20poetry/queer%20poetry/meditative%20poetry/2025/07/17/Selected-Poems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selected Poems - Constantine P. Cavafy" /><published>2025-07-17T12:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-17T12:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/modernist%20poetry/lyric%20poetry/elegy/philosophical%20poetry/historical%20poetry/symbolist%20poetry/queer%20poetry/meditative%20poetry/2025/07/17/Selected-Poems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/modernist%20poetry/lyric%20poetry/elegy/philosophical%20poetry/historical%20poetry/symbolist%20poetry/queer%20poetry/meditative%20poetry/2025/07/17/Selected-Poems/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Constantine P. Cavafy</strong> (1863–1933) was a Greek poet whose work blends history, personal memory, and quiet desire into a style both spare and deeply emotional. His poems often meditate on exile, the passing of time, and the elusive nature of meaning itself. Cavafy’s voice feels like a whisper from the past—calm yet haunting, distant yet intimately familiar. His influence stretches far beyond Greece, touching poets and readers worldwide with his subtle, layered elegies to lost moments and love.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/image/c.p.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/c.p.jpg" alt="Constantine P. Cavafy" /></a></p>

<p>Encountering Cavafy’s poetry felt like wandering through the ruins of an ancient city, bathed in soft sunlight, where every stone and shadow carries stories of loss, love, and choices made long ago. There’s a <em>quiet sadness</em> in his poems—an elegiac tone that acknowledges the relentless march of time and the impossibility of reclaiming what is lost. Yet this sadness is not overwhelming or despairing; instead, it offers a meditative calmness, as if the poet gently holds the weight of history and personal memory in his hands and exhales it slowly.</p>

<p>What stayed with me most was the profound sense of <em>detachment</em> in his voice. Cavafy often observes the world from a distance, watching empires crumble and loves fade, yet never fully immersing himself in the chaos. This detachment is not coldness but a form of deep introspection—like a scholar studying ruins, aware of both beauty and decay. The poems about cities, exile, and regret resonate with the sense that we carry our own ruin inside us, wherever we go.</p>

<p>His style is <em>remarkably sparse and powerful.</em> Each word is chosen with precision, and the poems often feel pared down to essentials—yet beneath this simplicity lies vast emotional and intellectual depth. Irony and philosophical questioning thread through especially his historical poems, inviting reflection on fate, destiny, and human folly.</p>

<p>In <em>The City</em>, Cavafy writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“You won’t find a new country, you won’t find another shore.<br />
This city will follow you wherever you go.”</em><br />
This line struck me profoundly. It captures the haunting truth that running away is futile; we cannot escape ourselves or our pasts. No matter how far we travel, the city—our personal history and burdens—shadows us relentlessly.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In <em>The Craftsman of Wine Bowls</em>, Cavafy meditates on art’s power to capture and preserve memory and longing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“The artist who made these wine bowls —<br />
they are still preserved, because he lived a long time ago —<br />
loved deeply, and loved long.”</em><br />
Here, love and memory are intertwined with creation. The poem suggests that though time erodes all things, art holds onto the intensity of human feeling, offering a fragile, beautiful immortality.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Another layer that stood out is the subtle, coded queerness running through many of the poems you read. It’s like peering through a fogged window at desire and intimacy that cannot be openly declared but pulses beneath the surface. This <em>understated longing</em> adds a poignant vulnerability and private sadness that complements the formal elegance of his style. It’s a quiet rebellion against silence and invisibility.</p>

<p>Reading Cavafy was like overhearing a conversation not meant for me—someone else’s regrets, dreams, and regrets whispered softly across time. It felt like watching the present unravel with the calm, knowing gaze of someone who’s seen how it all ends. There’s a haunting beauty in his deliberate withholding, the spaces between words that invite readers to fill them with their own memories and emotions.</p>

<p>Cavafy’s poetry offers no easy comforts or answers. It is a quiet elegy for what once was and what can never be again—a meditation on exile, regret, and the slow decay of all things. Yet it is also beautiful in its honesty, in its refusal to sugarcoat life’s complex emotional truths.</p>

<p>His poems do not clamor for attention. They seep into the mind like a faint but persistent light, leaving behind a sense of wonder mixed with melancholy. They ask you to sit with uncertainty, to embrace the ghosts of choices and the ache of unfulfilled desire.</p>

<p>Reading <em>C.P. Cavafy: Selected Poems</em> is like stepping into a realm where time folds and stories blend—where the personal becomes universal, and history is a mirror for the soul. It’s a poetic journey that lingers long after the last page.</p>

<p><strong>From “The City”:</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“You won’t find a new country, you won’t find another shore.<br />
This city will follow you wherever you go.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>From “Waiting for the Barbarians”:</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“What are we waiting for, assembled in the forum?<br />
The barbarians are due here today.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>From “The Horses of Achilles”:</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“How could I not weep when I saw<br />
those horses weep?”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>From “The Craftsman of Wine Bowls”:</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“The artist who made these wine bowls —<br />
they are still preserved, because he lived a long time ago —<br />
loved deeply, and loved long.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>From “The Tyanaean Sculptor”:</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“He carved the statue of Hermes<br />
with calm skill, and the very calm of his skill<br />
revealed a soul that had lived a long time.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>From “Beside the House”:</strong></p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I am neither a child, nor young anymore —<br />
yet the house is full of voices<br />
that call to me.”</em></p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Modernist poetry" /><category term="Lyric Poetry" /><category term="Elegy" /><category term="Philosophical Poetry" /><category term="Historical poetry" /><category term="Symbolist poetry" /><category term="Queer poetry" /><category term="Meditative poetry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Constantine P. Cavafy (1863–1933) was a Greek poet whose work blends history, personal memory, and quiet desire into a style both spare and deeply emotional. His poems often meditate on exile, the passing of time, and the elusive nature of meaning itself. Cavafy’s voice feels like a whisper from the past—calm yet haunting, distant yet intimately familiar. His influence stretches far beyond Greece, touching poets and readers worldwide with his subtle, layered elegies to lost moments and love. Encountering Cavafy’s poetry felt like wandering through the ruins of an ancient city, bathed in soft sunlight, where every stone and shadow carries stories of loss, love, and choices made long ago. There’s a quiet sadness in his poems—an elegiac tone that acknowledges the relentless march of time and the impossibility of reclaiming what is lost. Yet this sadness is not overwhelming or despairing; instead, it offers a meditative calmness, as if the poet gently holds the weight of history and personal memory in his hands and exhales it slowly. What stayed with me most was the profound sense of detachment in his voice. Cavafy often observes the world from a distance, watching empires crumble and loves fade, yet never fully immersing himself in the chaos. This detachment is not coldness but a form of deep introspection—like a scholar studying ruins, aware of both beauty and decay. The poems about cities, exile, and regret resonate with the sense that we carry our own ruin inside us, wherever we go. His style is remarkably sparse and powerful. Each word is chosen with precision, and the poems often feel pared down to essentials—yet beneath this simplicity lies vast emotional and intellectual depth. Irony and philosophical questioning thread through especially his historical poems, inviting reflection on fate, destiny, and human folly. In The City, Cavafy writes: “You won’t find a new country, you won’t find another shore. This city will follow you wherever you go.” This line struck me profoundly. It captures the haunting truth that running away is futile; we cannot escape ourselves or our pasts. No matter how far we travel, the city—our personal history and burdens—shadows us relentlessly. In The Craftsman of Wine Bowls, Cavafy meditates on art’s power to capture and preserve memory and longing: “The artist who made these wine bowls — they are still preserved, because he lived a long time ago — loved deeply, and loved long.” Here, love and memory are intertwined with creation. The poem suggests that though time erodes all things, art holds onto the intensity of human feeling, offering a fragile, beautiful immortality. Another layer that stood out is the subtle, coded queerness running through many of the poems you read. It’s like peering through a fogged window at desire and intimacy that cannot be openly declared but pulses beneath the surface. This understated longing adds a poignant vulnerability and private sadness that complements the formal elegance of his style. It’s a quiet rebellion against silence and invisibility. Reading Cavafy was like overhearing a conversation not meant for me—someone else’s regrets, dreams, and regrets whispered softly across time. It felt like watching the present unravel with the calm, knowing gaze of someone who’s seen how it all ends. There’s a haunting beauty in his deliberate withholding, the spaces between words that invite readers to fill them with their own memories and emotions. Cavafy’s poetry offers no easy comforts or answers. It is a quiet elegy for what once was and what can never be again—a meditation on exile, regret, and the slow decay of all things. Yet it is also beautiful in its honesty, in its refusal to sugarcoat life’s complex emotional truths. His poems do not clamor for attention. They seep into the mind like a faint but persistent light, leaving behind a sense of wonder mixed with melancholy. They ask you to sit with uncertainty, to embrace the ghosts of choices and the ache of unfulfilled desire. Reading C.P. Cavafy: Selected Poems is like stepping into a realm where time folds and stories blend—where the personal becomes universal, and history is a mirror for the soul. It’s a poetic journey that lingers long after the last page. From “The City”: “You won’t find a new country, you won’t find another shore. This city will follow you wherever you go.” From “Waiting for the Barbarians”: “What are we waiting for, assembled in the forum? The barbarians are due here today.” From “The Horses of Achilles”: “How could I not weep when I saw those horses weep?” From “The Craftsman of Wine Bowls”: “The artist who made these wine bowls — they are still preserved, because he lived a long time ago — loved deeply, and loved long.” From “The Tyanaean Sculptor”: “He carved the statue of Hermes with calm skill, and the very calm of his skill revealed a soul that had lived a long time.” From “Beside the House”: “I am neither a child, nor young anymore — yet the house is full of voices that call to me.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Judgment - Franz Kafka</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/franz%20kafka/psychological%20horror/absurdist/modernist/surreal%20/%20absurdist%20short%20stories/2025/07/17/The-Judgment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Judgment - Franz Kafka" /><published>2025-07-17T12:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-17T12:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/franz%20kafka/psychological%20horror/absurdist/modernist/surreal%20/%20absurdist%20short%20stories/2025/07/17/The-Judgment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/franz%20kafka/psychological%20horror/absurdist/modernist/surreal%20/%20absurdist%20short%20stories/2025/07/17/The-Judgment/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Franz Kafka</strong> (1883–1924) was a German-speaking writer from Prague, known for his haunting, often surreal stories about alienation, anxiety, and the absurdity of modern life. Though he published only a few works in his lifetime, his unique voice and dreamlike, unsettling style left a lasting impact on world literature. He’s best known for The Metamorphosis, The Trial, and The Castle — all of which explore characters trapped in bizarre, often unexplainable realities.</p>

<p>Today, “Kafkaesque” is a word we use to describe situations that feel illogical, oppressive, and quietly terrifying — the way his stories often do.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/image/franz.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/franz.jpg" alt="Franz Kafka" /></a></p>

<p>This story is short, maybe 10–12 pages, but it left me shaken. <em>The Judgment</em> feels like a private nightmare you’re not meant to witness — a kind of mental implosion, disguised as a simple conversation between father and son.</p>

<p>It starts quietly enough. Georg Bendemann, the son, writes a letter to a friend abroad, and then chats with his aging father. But the scene flips quickly. The father, who seemed weak and confused, suddenly becomes powerful—rising like some ancient judge. He accuses Georg of betrayal, of hypocrisy, of shame—and we never quite understand <em>why</em>. And maybe we’re not supposed to.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“So now you know what else existed in the world outside of yourself. Till now you knew only about yourself!”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That line hit me hard. It’s not just a father yelling at his son—it’s the voice of some invisible force reminding you of how small, selfish, and powerless you really are. It’s guilt with no anchor. Punishment without logic. And what’s worse? It <em>feels</em> true, even if it doesn’t make sense.</p>

<p>I kept thinking: is this about authority? About Kafka’s own father? About a man finally collapsing under invisible pressures? All of them, probably. The story refuses to give a clean answer.</p>

<p>And the ending — sudden, violent, and bizarre — left me uneasy. Not horrified, just… wrong-footed. Like I’d just read a suicide note written in metaphor.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“And he let himself drop. At this moment an unending stream of traffic was just going over the bridge.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That last sentence is Kafka in a nutshell. A man jumps to his death, and the world rolls on.</p>

<p>There’s a quiet terror in that. No drama. Just the judgment, the fall, and silence.</p>

<p>This isn’t a story that explains itself. It just happens—like a bad dream that feels too personal to ignore. I didn’t <em>understand</em> it fully, and maybe I’m not supposed to. But I felt something: a cold weight, a sadness, a pressure. Like guilt without a name.</p>

<p>Kafka doesn’t write monsters. He writes about the systems that make us feel monstrous.</p>

<p>And in <em>The Judgment</em>, the system is the family. The father. The self.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You wanted to cover me up, but I’m not so easily covered up.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Because the world is as it is, it is impossible to live in it without failing to act sinfully.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I always knew you were a hypocrite, and now the Supreme Judge has punished you.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“At this moment an unending stream of traffic was just going over the bridge.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Franz Kafka" /><category term="Psychological Horror" /><category term="Absurdist" /><category term="Modernist" /><category term="Surreal / Absurdist Short Stories" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Franz Kafka (1883–1924) was a German-speaking writer from Prague, known for his haunting, often surreal stories about alienation, anxiety, and the absurdity of modern life. Though he published only a few works in his lifetime, his unique voice and dreamlike, unsettling style left a lasting impact on world literature. He’s best known for The Metamorphosis, The Trial, and The Castle — all of which explore characters trapped in bizarre, often unexplainable realities. Today, “Kafkaesque” is a word we use to describe situations that feel illogical, oppressive, and quietly terrifying — the way his stories often do. This story is short, maybe 10–12 pages, but it left me shaken. The Judgment feels like a private nightmare you’re not meant to witness — a kind of mental implosion, disguised as a simple conversation between father and son. It starts quietly enough. Georg Bendemann, the son, writes a letter to a friend abroad, and then chats with his aging father. But the scene flips quickly. The father, who seemed weak and confused, suddenly becomes powerful—rising like some ancient judge. He accuses Georg of betrayal, of hypocrisy, of shame—and we never quite understand why. And maybe we’re not supposed to. “So now you know what else existed in the world outside of yourself. Till now you knew only about yourself!” That line hit me hard. It’s not just a father yelling at his son—it’s the voice of some invisible force reminding you of how small, selfish, and powerless you really are. It’s guilt with no anchor. Punishment without logic. And what’s worse? It feels true, even if it doesn’t make sense. I kept thinking: is this about authority? About Kafka’s own father? About a man finally collapsing under invisible pressures? All of them, probably. The story refuses to give a clean answer. And the ending — sudden, violent, and bizarre — left me uneasy. Not horrified, just… wrong-footed. Like I’d just read a suicide note written in metaphor. “And he let himself drop. At this moment an unending stream of traffic was just going over the bridge.” That last sentence is Kafka in a nutshell. A man jumps to his death, and the world rolls on. There’s a quiet terror in that. No drama. Just the judgment, the fall, and silence. This isn’t a story that explains itself. It just happens—like a bad dream that feels too personal to ignore. I didn’t understand it fully, and maybe I’m not supposed to. But I felt something: a cold weight, a sadness, a pressure. Like guilt without a name. Kafka doesn’t write monsters. He writes about the systems that make us feel monstrous. And in The Judgment, the system is the family. The father. The self. “You wanted to cover me up, but I’m not so easily covered up.” “Because the world is as it is, it is impossible to live in it without failing to act sinfully.” “I always knew you were a hypocrite, and now the Supreme Judge has punished you.” “At this moment an unending stream of traffic was just going over the bridge.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Martian Chronicles - Ray Bradbury</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science%20fiction/speculative%20fiction/dystopian%20myth/sci-fi/dystopia/mars/2025/07/16/The-Martian-Chronicles/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Martian Chronicles - Ray Bradbury" /><published>2025-07-16T03:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-16T03:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science%20fiction/speculative%20fiction/dystopian%20myth/sci-fi/dystopia/mars/2025/07/16/The-Martian-Chronicles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science%20fiction/speculative%20fiction/dystopian%20myth/sci-fi/dystopia/mars/2025/07/16/The-Martian-Chronicles/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Ray Bradbury</strong> was an American writer of speculative fiction, best known for his lyrical, haunting explorations of technology, nostalgia, and the darker corners of the human imagination. From dystopian futures to Martian landscapes to quiet Midwestern towns with strange secrets, Bradbury’s stories often blur the line between science fiction and poetic fable. “The Veldt” (1950), one of his most iconic short stories, first appeared in <em>The Saturday Evening Post</em> before becoming part of his collection <em>The Illustrated Man</em>. A chilling blend of futurism and family horror, it remains disturbingly relevant today.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="/assets/image/ray.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/ray.jpg" alt="Ray Bradbury" /></a></p>

<p>Every story in <em>The Martian Chronicles</em> feels like it’s made of silence. Even the moments of action carry a strange quiet. A sadness that just hangs in the air, like the dust on Mars.</p>

<p>What stayed with me most was the <em>loneliness</em>. Not just of the planet—but of the people. Everyone seems to be running from something. From war, from guilt, from Earth. And when they get to Mars, they don’t find peace. They just find more distance. There’s beauty, yes. But it’s the kind of beauty that makes you ache.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“There was a thing to be done, and when it was over, it was done. They shut the door and stood in the night air of Mars, listening to the voices and the wind.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>The stories don’t build toward one big climax. They echo. They layer. I loved that. Each piece gave me something different—a mood, a question, a scar. The structure worked like memory: fragmented, incomplete, but meaningful in the gaps. It doesn’t hold your hand. It just lets you feel.</p>

<p>And the Martians… I don’t even know if I understood them. But maybe that’s the point. They felt like poems that knew they were going extinct. They’re barely present by the second half of the book, but their absence weighs more than their presence. And when they do appear, they’re distant, strange, full of quiet wisdom. Like they already saw the ending.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“We Earth Men have a talent for ruining big, beautiful things.”</em><br />
That line might as well be the book’s thesis. It’s a slow-motion tragedy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I read “Way in the Middle of the Air” too—the original 1950 version that Bradbury later replaced. It’s uncomfortable and raw. Ugly, even. But in that ugliness, there’s a sharp truth: how deeply hate can twist a person, and how powerful it is to simply <em>leave</em>. That scene of mass migration—of Black Americans leaving Earth to escape racism, not just hoping Mars will be different, but believing they can remake life itself—was deeply sad and oddly uplifting at once.</p>

<p>I also read “The Fire Balloons,” which flips the missionary story on its head. The idea that Martians might be pure, sinless beings made of light—and that maybe we came to “save” them when we’re the ones who need saving—that was one of the most quiet and brilliant turns in the whole book.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“We’ve never had to prove the truth of our faith. We’ve only had to feel it.”</em><br />
Bradbury writes religion as something both sincere and dangerous. And in that tension, he finds something real.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The tone of the book is lyrical. Sometimes too lyrical. There were times I wished Bradbury would get out of his own way—stop describing and let the story move. But even when it felt overwritten, it still worked emotionally. Like a lullaby for a dying planet.</p>

<p>My Final Thought - Reading <em>The Martian Chronicles</em> felt like waking up from a dream I didn’t know I was having—and then wanting to go back to sleep just to feel it again. It made me nostalgic for something I’ve never known. Like I lost something I didn’t even realize I’d loved.</p>

<p>It’s not a book that explains. It just shows you images, gives you silences, leaves you alone with them. But in those spaces—between Earth and Mars, between memory and regret—Bradbury says something profound:<br />
That if we don’t change, we’ll take our emptiness everywhere we go. Even to the stars.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“Mars was a distant shore, and the men spread upon it in waves.”</em><br />
Colonization as a slow tide—inevitable, careless.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“We Earth Men have a talent for ruining big, beautiful things.”</em><br />
The sentence that lingers long after you close the book.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“There will come soft rains and the smell of the ground, and swallows circling with their shimmering sound…”</em><br />
From the story where only the house remains. No people. Just ghosts made of automation. That one chilled me.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“I was a poet in the land of the dead.”</em><br />
And isn’t that what Bradbury himself was?</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Science Fiction" /><category term="speculative fiction" /><category term="dystopian myth" /><category term="Sci-Fi" /><category term="Dystopia" /><category term="Mars" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ray Bradbury was an American writer of speculative fiction, best known for his lyrical, haunting explorations of technology, nostalgia, and the darker corners of the human imagination. From dystopian futures to Martian landscapes to quiet Midwestern towns with strange secrets, Bradbury’s stories often blur the line between science fiction and poetic fable. “The Veldt” (1950), one of his most iconic short stories, first appeared in The Saturday Evening Post before becoming part of his collection The Illustrated Man. A chilling blend of futurism and family horror, it remains disturbingly relevant today. Every story in The Martian Chronicles feels like it’s made of silence. Even the moments of action carry a strange quiet. A sadness that just hangs in the air, like the dust on Mars. What stayed with me most was the loneliness. Not just of the planet—but of the people. Everyone seems to be running from something. From war, from guilt, from Earth. And when they get to Mars, they don’t find peace. They just find more distance. There’s beauty, yes. But it’s the kind of beauty that makes you ache. “There was a thing to be done, and when it was over, it was done. They shut the door and stood in the night air of Mars, listening to the voices and the wind.” The stories don’t build toward one big climax. They echo. They layer. I loved that. Each piece gave me something different—a mood, a question, a scar. The structure worked like memory: fragmented, incomplete, but meaningful in the gaps. It doesn’t hold your hand. It just lets you feel. And the Martians… I don’t even know if I understood them. But maybe that’s the point. They felt like poems that knew they were going extinct. They’re barely present by the second half of the book, but their absence weighs more than their presence. And when they do appear, they’re distant, strange, full of quiet wisdom. Like they already saw the ending. “We Earth Men have a talent for ruining big, beautiful things.” That line might as well be the book’s thesis. It’s a slow-motion tragedy. I read “Way in the Middle of the Air” too—the original 1950 version that Bradbury later replaced. It’s uncomfortable and raw. Ugly, even. But in that ugliness, there’s a sharp truth: how deeply hate can twist a person, and how powerful it is to simply leave. That scene of mass migration—of Black Americans leaving Earth to escape racism, not just hoping Mars will be different, but believing they can remake life itself—was deeply sad and oddly uplifting at once. I also read “The Fire Balloons,” which flips the missionary story on its head. The idea that Martians might be pure, sinless beings made of light—and that maybe we came to “save” them when we’re the ones who need saving—that was one of the most quiet and brilliant turns in the whole book. “We’ve never had to prove the truth of our faith. We’ve only had to feel it.” Bradbury writes religion as something both sincere and dangerous. And in that tension, he finds something real. The tone of the book is lyrical. Sometimes too lyrical. There were times I wished Bradbury would get out of his own way—stop describing and let the story move. But even when it felt overwritten, it still worked emotionally. Like a lullaby for a dying planet. My Final Thought - Reading The Martian Chronicles felt like waking up from a dream I didn’t know I was having—and then wanting to go back to sleep just to feel it again. It made me nostalgic for something I’ve never known. Like I lost something I didn’t even realize I’d loved. It’s not a book that explains. It just shows you images, gives you silences, leaves you alone with them. But in those spaces—between Earth and Mars, between memory and regret—Bradbury says something profound: That if we don’t change, we’ll take our emptiness everywhere we go. Even to the stars. “Mars was a distant shore, and the men spread upon it in waves.” Colonization as a slow tide—inevitable, careless. “We Earth Men have a talent for ruining big, beautiful things.” The sentence that lingers long after you close the book. “There will come soft rains and the smell of the ground, and swallows circling with their shimmering sound…” From the story where only the house remains. No people. Just ghosts made of automation. That one chilled me. “I was a poet in the land of the dead.” And isn’t that what Bradbury himself was?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep? - Philip K. Dick</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/science%20fiction/dystopia/existentialism/androids/2025/07/12/Do-Androids-Dream-of-Electric-Sheep/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep? - Philip K. Dick" /><published>2025-07-12T03:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-12T03:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science%20fiction/dystopia/existentialism/androids/2025/07/12/Do-Androids-Dream-of-Electric-Sheep</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/science%20fiction/dystopia/existentialism/androids/2025/07/12/Do-Androids-Dream-of-Electric-Sheep/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Philip K. Dick</strong> (1928–1982) was one of the most original and mind-bending voices in 20th-century science fiction. American, paranoid, visionary — he blurred the lines between reality and illusion in nearly every story he wrote. Though he lived in relative obscurity and struggled with mental health and substance use, his ideas outlived him in a big way — influencing everything from <em>Blade Runner</em> to <em>The Matrix</em> to modern AI discourse. His work doesn’t feel like polished sci-fi; it feels like a dream unraveling.</p>

<p>Recurring themes? Identity, reality, empathy, surveillance, and the terrifying thought that you might not be who you think you are. His worlds are crumbling, synthetic, and often heartbreakingly human.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="/assets/image/k.dick.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/k.dick.jpg" alt="Philip K. Dick" /></a></p>

<p>This book feels like walking through a dream after the end of the world. Nothing is fully alive, nothing fully dead. Just the echo of things that used to matter.</p>

<p>Deckard is supposed to be the protagonist, but he doesn’t feel like a hero. He feels like a man quietly falling apart. There’s something almost pitiable about him—someone trying so hard to feel human in a place that’s forgotten how. I didn’t admire him, but I felt something for him. That sadness of going through the motions and still hoping it means something.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I just want to go home before dark.”<br />
One of the simplest lines in the book, but it hit me. It’s not about the mission or some big moral awakening. He’s just tired. Worn down. That feeling runs deep through this story.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Dick sets empathy as the dividing line between androids and humans—but then blurs it until it disappears. The humans in this book are cold, transactional, self-absorbed. They hunt androids with no remorse. They fake their emotions using mood organs. They obsess over owning animals to seem “alive,” not because they care about life.</p>

<p>The irony is brutal: the androids are supposed to be less than human, but they seem more desperate to <em>belong</em>. They’re confused, frightened, sometimes even tender. The humans? They seem to have outsourced their souls.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You will be required to do wrong no matter where you go. It is the basic condition of life…”<br />
That line haunted me. Because that’s what this book is really about—not action, not androids, not even empathy. It’s about compromise. That no matter how much you try to stay clean, the world will make you dirty. And you’ll still have to get up and keep moving.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The animals are a whole other layer. They’re sacred now. A sign that you’re still part of life. But so many of them are fake—and everyone knows it, but pretends not to. There’s something tragically funny about that. Like the world has collapsed, but social status still matters more than truth. You’re not judged by your empathy—you’re judged by whether your sheep eats real hay.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Do you have any real animals?”<br />
The question sounds so simple, but in this world, it’s like asking: <em>Are you still human? Are you still trying to care about anything at all?</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>And then there’s the ending. It doesn’t tie anything up. Deckard stumbles into the desert. He finds a toad—a sacred animal—and you think: here it is. Something real. Something alive. And then it turns out to be fake. A machine. Just another replica. But he doesn’t throw it away. He still brings it home. Still wants to believe in it. That crushed me.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The silence of the world could not rein back its greed.”<br />
It’s like the universe has given up, but the humans haven’t. They keep reaching for meaning in a place that no longer offers it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s what makes this story feel so existential. There are no grand revelations, no triumphant awakenings. Just the slow grind of choices, moral compromises, and the need—however irrational—to keep going.</p>

<p>This isn’t sci-fi that answers questions. It <em>becomes</em> them. And that’s what lingers.</p>

<p>My Final Thought - Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep?_ isn’t a clean novel. It’s jagged, eerie, and strange. But there’s a bleak beauty in it. Even in a world of dust and replicas, people still try to feel. Still try to care. And even if the toad is fake, the need to hold it, to protect it—that’s real.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“You will be required to do wrong no matter where you go. It is the basic condition of life, to be required to violate your own identity.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“An android doesn’t care what happens to another android. That’s one of the indications we look for.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The silence of the world could not rein back its greed.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Do you have any real animals?”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I don’t care,” he said. “I just want to go home before dark.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Everything is true,” he said. “Everything anybody has ever thought.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Science fiction" /><category term="Dystopia" /><category term="existentialism" /><category term="Androids" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Philip K. Dick (1928–1982) was one of the most original and mind-bending voices in 20th-century science fiction. American, paranoid, visionary — he blurred the lines between reality and illusion in nearly every story he wrote. Though he lived in relative obscurity and struggled with mental health and substance use, his ideas outlived him in a big way — influencing everything from Blade Runner to The Matrix to modern AI discourse. His work doesn’t feel like polished sci-fi; it feels like a dream unraveling. Recurring themes? Identity, reality, empathy, surveillance, and the terrifying thought that you might not be who you think you are. His worlds are crumbling, synthetic, and often heartbreakingly human. This book feels like walking through a dream after the end of the world. Nothing is fully alive, nothing fully dead. Just the echo of things that used to matter. Deckard is supposed to be the protagonist, but he doesn’t feel like a hero. He feels like a man quietly falling apart. There’s something almost pitiable about him—someone trying so hard to feel human in a place that’s forgotten how. I didn’t admire him, but I felt something for him. That sadness of going through the motions and still hoping it means something. “I just want to go home before dark.” One of the simplest lines in the book, but it hit me. It’s not about the mission or some big moral awakening. He’s just tired. Worn down. That feeling runs deep through this story. Dick sets empathy as the dividing line between androids and humans—but then blurs it until it disappears. The humans in this book are cold, transactional, self-absorbed. They hunt androids with no remorse. They fake their emotions using mood organs. They obsess over owning animals to seem “alive,” not because they care about life. The irony is brutal: the androids are supposed to be less than human, but they seem more desperate to belong. They’re confused, frightened, sometimes even tender. The humans? They seem to have outsourced their souls. “You will be required to do wrong no matter where you go. It is the basic condition of life…” That line haunted me. Because that’s what this book is really about—not action, not androids, not even empathy. It’s about compromise. That no matter how much you try to stay clean, the world will make you dirty. And you’ll still have to get up and keep moving. The animals are a whole other layer. They’re sacred now. A sign that you’re still part of life. But so many of them are fake—and everyone knows it, but pretends not to. There’s something tragically funny about that. Like the world has collapsed, but social status still matters more than truth. You’re not judged by your empathy—you’re judged by whether your sheep eats real hay. “Do you have any real animals?” The question sounds so simple, but in this world, it’s like asking: Are you still human? Are you still trying to care about anything at all? And then there’s the ending. It doesn’t tie anything up. Deckard stumbles into the desert. He finds a toad—a sacred animal—and you think: here it is. Something real. Something alive. And then it turns out to be fake. A machine. Just another replica. But he doesn’t throw it away. He still brings it home. Still wants to believe in it. That crushed me. “The silence of the world could not rein back its greed.” It’s like the universe has given up, but the humans haven’t. They keep reaching for meaning in a place that no longer offers it. That’s what makes this story feel so existential. There are no grand revelations, no triumphant awakenings. Just the slow grind of choices, moral compromises, and the need—however irrational—to keep going. This isn’t sci-fi that answers questions. It becomes them. And that’s what lingers. My Final Thought - Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep?_ isn’t a clean novel. It’s jagged, eerie, and strange. But there’s a bleak beauty in it. Even in a world of dust and replicas, people still try to feel. Still try to care. And even if the toad is fake, the need to hold it, to protect it—that’s real. “You will be required to do wrong no matter where you go. It is the basic condition of life, to be required to violate your own identity.” “An android doesn’t care what happens to another android. That’s one of the indications we look for.” “The silence of the world could not rein back its greed.” “Do you have any real animals?” “I don’t care,” he said. “I just want to go home before dark.” “Everything is true,” he said. “Everything anybody has ever thought.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Guest - Albert Camus</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/existential%20fiction/philosophical%20short%20story/postcolonial%20literature/absurdist%20fiction/allegorical%20narrative/2025/07/08/The-Guest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Guest - Albert Camus" /><published>2025-07-08T03:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T03:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/existential%20fiction/philosophical%20short%20story/postcolonial%20literature/absurdist%20fiction/allegorical%20narrative/2025/07/08/The-Guest</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/existential%20fiction/philosophical%20short%20story/postcolonial%20literature/absurdist%20fiction/allegorical%20narrative/2025/07/08/The-Guest/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Albert Camus</strong> (1913–1960) was a French-Algerian philosopher, novelist, and journalist — often associated with <strong>existentialism</strong>, though he preferred the label <strong>absurdist</strong>. He wrote about alienation, freedom, and the human struggle to make sense of a senseless world. Best known for <em>The Stranger</em>, <em>The Plague</em>, and <em>The Myth of Sisyphus</em>, Camus’s work feels like moral philosophy disguised as fiction — but it never sacrifices feeling for theory.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="/assets/image/camus.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/camus.jpg" alt="Albert Camus" /></a>
There’s something so clever in the title alone — <em>L’Hôte</em> in French means both <em>guest</em> and <em>host</em>. That ambiguity is exactly what makes this story hum beneath the surface. Nothing here is settled, not even the roles people think they’re playing.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“No. I’m going back to El Ameur. And you will deliver this fellow to Tinguit. He is expected at police headquarters.”<br />
Balducci was looking at Daru with a friendly little smile.<br />
“What’s this story?” asked the schoolmaster. “Are you pulling my leg?”<br />
“No, son. Those are the orders.”<br />
“The orders? I’m not . . .” Daru hesitated, not wanting to hurt the old Corsican. “I mean, that’s not my job.”<br />
“What! What’s the meaning of that? In wartime people do all kinds of jobs.”<br />
“Then I’ll wait for the declaration of war!”<br />
Balducci nodded. “O. K. But the orders exist and they concern you too. Things are brewing, it appears. There is talk of a forthcoming revolt. . . . “</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>The Guest</em> is set in Algeria — Camus’ own terrain — during the early rumblings of the war for independence. But this isn’t a war story, not really. It’s stripped down. A teacher, a prisoner, a desert. No big speeches. Just a quiet crisis: deliver the prisoner, or don’t. Choose a side, or pretend not to.</p>

<p>But of course, not choosing <em>is</em> a choice.</p>

<p><a href="/assets/image/camustheguest.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/camustheguest.jpg" alt="A snow-bound Berber village in the Atlas mountains, in 2018" /></a></p>

<p>Camus doesn’t beat you over the head with it — he just places you in this cold, dusty room of a story and lets you feel the weight. The absurdity of it all. That whatever you do, there’s no real winning. You’re accountable either way. People will hate you either way.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Men who share the same rooms, soldiers or prisoners, develop a strange alliance as if, having cast off their armor with their clothing, they fraternized every evening, over and above their differences, in the ancient community of dream and fatigue.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s only ten pages, but somehow Camus squeezes in the entire human condition. That’s what hit me. This bleak beauty — where life’s just a series of meaningless choices made under a sky that doesn’t care, and yet… we still have to choose.</p>

<p>The ending? Open. Unresolved. Perfect. Just like life.
A snow-bound Berber village in the Atlas mountains, in 2018</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“You handed over our brother. You will pay for this.”</em><br />
Chilling. Even neutrality is a choice — and it has consequences.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“He felt like a schoolmaster again with a rebellious student.”</em><br />
So much is packed into this. Power. Helplessness. That gap between what you want to do and what you’re forced to do.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“No one in this desert, neither he nor the Arab, mattered.”</em><br />
The Camus-core line. That existential shrug against a backdrop of moral chaos.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Existential Fiction" /><category term="Philosophical Short Story" /><category term="Postcolonial Literature" /><category term="Absurdist Fiction" /><category term="Allegorical Narrative" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Albert Camus (1913–1960) was a French-Algerian philosopher, novelist, and journalist — often associated with existentialism, though he preferred the label absurdist. He wrote about alienation, freedom, and the human struggle to make sense of a senseless world. Best known for The Stranger, The Plague, and The Myth of Sisyphus, Camus’s work feels like moral philosophy disguised as fiction — but it never sacrifices feeling for theory. There’s something so clever in the title alone — L’Hôte in French means both guest and host. That ambiguity is exactly what makes this story hum beneath the surface. Nothing here is settled, not even the roles people think they’re playing. “No. I’m going back to El Ameur. And you will deliver this fellow to Tinguit. He is expected at police headquarters.” Balducci was looking at Daru with a friendly little smile. “What’s this story?” asked the schoolmaster. “Are you pulling my leg?” “No, son. Those are the orders.” “The orders? I’m not . . .” Daru hesitated, not wanting to hurt the old Corsican. “I mean, that’s not my job.” “What! What’s the meaning of that? In wartime people do all kinds of jobs.” “Then I’ll wait for the declaration of war!” Balducci nodded. “O. K. But the orders exist and they concern you too. Things are brewing, it appears. There is talk of a forthcoming revolt. . . . “ The Guest is set in Algeria — Camus’ own terrain — during the early rumblings of the war for independence. But this isn’t a war story, not really. It’s stripped down. A teacher, a prisoner, a desert. No big speeches. Just a quiet crisis: deliver the prisoner, or don’t. Choose a side, or pretend not to. But of course, not choosing is a choice. Camus doesn’t beat you over the head with it — he just places you in this cold, dusty room of a story and lets you feel the weight. The absurdity of it all. That whatever you do, there’s no real winning. You’re accountable either way. People will hate you either way. “Men who share the same rooms, soldiers or prisoners, develop a strange alliance as if, having cast off their armor with their clothing, they fraternized every evening, over and above their differences, in the ancient community of dream and fatigue.” It’s only ten pages, but somehow Camus squeezes in the entire human condition. That’s what hit me. This bleak beauty — where life’s just a series of meaningless choices made under a sky that doesn’t care, and yet… we still have to choose. The ending? Open. Unresolved. Perfect. Just like life. A snow-bound Berber village in the Atlas mountains, in 2018 “You handed over our brother. You will pay for this.” Chilling. Even neutrality is a choice — and it has consequences. “He felt like a schoolmaster again with a rebellious student.” So much is packed into this. Power. Helplessness. That gap between what you want to do and what you’re forced to do. “No one in this desert, neither he nor the Arab, mattered.” The Camus-core line. That existential shrug against a backdrop of moral chaos.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can’t And Won’t - Lydia Davis</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flash%20fiction%20/%20microfiction/experimental%20fiction/literary%20minimalism/surreal%20/%20absurdist%20short%20stories/contemporary%20american%20literature/2025/07/08/Can't-And-Won't/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can’t And Won’t - Lydia Davis" /><published>2025-07-08T03:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-07-08T03:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flash%20fiction%20/%20microfiction/experimental%20fiction/literary%20minimalism/surreal%20/%20absurdist%20short%20stories/contemporary%20american%20literature/2025/07/08/Can&apos;t-And-Won&apos;t</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flash%20fiction%20/%20microfiction/experimental%20fiction/literary%20minimalism/surreal%20/%20absurdist%20short%20stories/contemporary%20american%20literature/2025/07/08/Can&apos;t-And-Won&apos;t/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Lydia Davis</strong> is known for writing some of the shortest stories you’ll ever read — and some of the most polarizing. A master of <strong>microfiction</strong>, she blends observation, dry humor, and everyday moments into strange little vignettes. Critics love her. She’s won a MacArthur “Genius” Grant. But her work often divides readers: you either sink into her fragmented world or bounce off it completely.</p>

<hr />

<p><a href="/assets/image/Ldavis.jpg" class="glightbox"><img src="/assets/image/Ldavis.jpg" alt="Lydia Davis" /></a></p>
<h3 id="answer-cant-and-wont"><strong>ANSWER: <em>Can’t and Won’t</em></strong></h3>

<p><strong>QUESTION: Will I read another book of “stories” by Lydia Davis?</strong></p>

<p>You know when you’re scrolling Goodreads, and you see all these people raving about something — 4 stars, 5 stars, calling it <em>brilliant</em> — so you think, <em>Okay, maybe I’ll keep going</em>? That was me. I kept reading, waiting for that switch to flip. Spoiler: it never did.</p>

<p>This book… I don’t even know where to start. Pages and pages about cows standing around. Obituaries turned into filler. That <em>Letter to the Foundation</em> piece? Never-ending. I forced myself through more than I wanted to, hoping for some kind of payoff or epiphany — but honestly, I don’t think there’s anything <em>to</em> get.</p>

<p>A friend warned me. Said Davis might not be for me. They were right. Maybe some of her other work hits differently, and I’d still give it a chance someday. But <em>this</em> book? Felt like a chore. I’ve done more interesting things than read this, including staring at my ceiling.</p>

<p>The writing didn’t move me. The stories — if you can even call them that — felt flat, dull, and painfully unoriginal. The book was like a burnt biscuit. No jam, no butter, nothing could save it. And the fluffier it got, the more burned I felt.</p>

<p>I rarely say I <em>hate</em> a book. But here we are. It wasn’t just a bad read — it was lifeless. Wordy in all the wrong ways. Some longer pieces dragged on, and I kept thinking they could’ve been trimmed into a single sentence or scrapped altogether. I don’t even mind wordy or meandering prose when there’s <em>something</em> to hold onto. But this had nothing — the imagery didn’t land, the diction was weak, and most of it felt like placeholders instead of finished thoughts.</p>

<p>Weirdly, the beginning wasn’t terrible. It gave me a sliver of hope. But I didn’t finish. I couldn’t. The disappointment was too real. I usually have a rule: if I buy a book, I finish it. But luckily, I didn’t pay for this one — it was just sitting in my EPUB files. And I’m glad I didn’t waste money on it.</p>

<p>I ain’t even leaving her Quotes.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Flash Fiction / Microfiction" /><category term="Experimental Fiction" /><category term="Literary Minimalism" /><category term="Surreal / Absurdist Short Stories" /><category term="Contemporary American Literature" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lydia Davis is known for writing some of the shortest stories you’ll ever read — and some of the most polarizing. A master of microfiction, she blends observation, dry humor, and everyday moments into strange little vignettes. Critics love her. She’s won a MacArthur “Genius” Grant. But her work often divides readers: you either sink into her fragmented world or bounce off it completely. ANSWER: Can’t and Won’t QUESTION: Will I read another book of “stories” by Lydia Davis? You know when you’re scrolling Goodreads, and you see all these people raving about something — 4 stars, 5 stars, calling it brilliant — so you think, Okay, maybe I’ll keep going? That was me. I kept reading, waiting for that switch to flip. Spoiler: it never did. This book… I don’t even know where to start. Pages and pages about cows standing around. Obituaries turned into filler. That Letter to the Foundation piece? Never-ending. I forced myself through more than I wanted to, hoping for some kind of payoff or epiphany — but honestly, I don’t think there’s anything to get. A friend warned me. Said Davis might not be for me. They were right. Maybe some of her other work hits differently, and I’d still give it a chance someday. But this book? Felt like a chore. I’ve done more interesting things than read this, including staring at my ceiling. The writing didn’t move me. The stories — if you can even call them that — felt flat, dull, and painfully unoriginal. The book was like a burnt biscuit. No jam, no butter, nothing could save it. And the fluffier it got, the more burned I felt. I rarely say I hate a book. But here we are. It wasn’t just a bad read — it was lifeless. Wordy in all the wrong ways. Some longer pieces dragged on, and I kept thinking they could’ve been trimmed into a single sentence or scrapped altogether. I don’t even mind wordy or meandering prose when there’s something to hold onto. But this had nothing — the imagery didn’t land, the diction was weak, and most of it felt like placeholders instead of finished thoughts. Weirdly, the beginning wasn’t terrible. It gave me a sliver of hope. But I didn’t finish. I couldn’t. The disappointment was too real. I usually have a rule: if I buy a book, I finish it. But luckily, I didn’t pay for this one — it was just sitting in my EPUB files. And I’m glad I didn’t waste money on it. I ain’t even leaving her Quotes.]]></summary></entry></feed>